Henry Street Music School records, 1927-1969
University of Minnesota Libraries
Henry Street Music School records
1927 1969
University of Minnesota. Social Welfare History Archives. [swha]
Henry Street Music School
47.25 linear feet
The Henry Street Settlement Music School records contain correspondence, financial records, reports, statistics and scrapbooks. Also includes card files with student and faculty information.
SW0116
Use of Materials
Open for use in Social Welfare History Archives reading room.
Acquisition Information
The Henry Street Settlement Music School records were received as a gift from the school in 1970 and 1975.
Other Finding Aid
Unpublished inventory available. Please contact Archives for more information.
Related Material
In addition to the above-described records of the Music School, the Social Welfare History Archives holds the records of Henry Street Settlement, the parent institution. These records contain scattered references to activities of the Music School as well as the Playhouse, whose dramatic productions often involved the Music School.
Historical Note
The Music School of Henry Street Settlement was formed in 1927, although the Settlement had offered musical activities for residents of New York City's Lower East Side for many years. The new school, which opened to students in the fall of 1928, offered classes in instrumental and vocal music, dancing, and instrument construction and repair.
Scope and Content
The Henry Street Music School records demonstrate the school's determination to provide both excellence in individual instruction (as evidenced in the number of its students who went on to professional careers) and diverse musical activities that would appeal to all sectors of the community. Among the special events and projects documented in the records are the school's 1937 world premiere performance of Aaron Copland's opera, The Second Hurricane (Copland was a member of the school's advisory committee as were George Gershwin and Jascha Heifetz), and a 1960s project to allow young men released from the Riker's Island Prison for young offenders to continue the instrumental lessons they had begun while incarcerated.
The bulk of the records comprises scrapbooks of programs, photographs, and clippings from recitals, productions, and other performances and card files containing basic information on individual students and faculty members. Also included in the records are annual reports, committee minutes, correspondence, financial records, statistical reports on students, and loose programs and photographs. The individuals represented most prominently in the records are three of the school's directors: Hedi Katz (1927-1935); Grace Spofford (1935-1954); and Robert Egan (1954-1969).
Index Terms
This Henry Street Music School records are indexed under the following headings in the catalog of the University of Minnesota Libraries. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Henry Street Settlement (New York, N.Y.). Music School; Henry Street Settlement (New York, N.Y.). Music School Records.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); Music Instruction and study New York (State) New York History Sources.; Social settlements New York (State) New York History Sources.
Detailed Description of the Records
- Series 1: Administrative Materials, 1927-1967
  Series 1 consists of three record storage boxes of administrative records of the Music School. Materials in series 1 include correspondence financial records, reports and statistics.
  - Self Study, History of Music School and Playhouse, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Self-Study, History of Music School and Playhouse, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Self-Study, History of Music School and Playhouse, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - New York State Material: State Education Department Approval for Veterans, 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New York State Material: State Education Department Approval for Veterans, 1953, 1955, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Veterans Material, 1946-1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Veterans Material, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Veterans List, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New York State War Service Scholarship for Veterans, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Teachers' Salaries, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Monday Staff Meetings, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Music School Faculty Manual, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Concerts, Book Bazar, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Violin Faculty Meeting, November 10, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Chamber Ensemble, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Financial, Enrollment, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Riker's Island Project, 1963-1967
    - Indiana State Prison
    - Program (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lists of Instruments rented out (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Participation Charts (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence and Reports (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - List of Students, Attendance Logs, Instrument Rentals (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lists, Reports, and Statistical Summaries (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lists, Attendance Logs (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, Financial, Miscellaneous, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Financial, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Expenditures and 1929-1933 Enrollment (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, Financial, Executive Meeting Minutes, Miscellaneous, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, Financial, Executive Meeting Minutes, Miscellaneous, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, Financial, Miscellaneous, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, Financial, Executive Meeting Minutes, Miscellaneous, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Folio - Financial, 1929, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Brochures from Other Settlement Music Schools, 1954-1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Programs, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Schedules and Plans, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Arnold Pomerantz Memorial Fund Scholarship (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Tennyson and other Competition Award Applicants, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - LaGuardia Music Scholarship: Correspondence, Students, Tests, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - LaGuardia Music Scholarship Candidates, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - LaGuardia Music Scholarship, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Music Scholarship Committee, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Music Scholarship Committee, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Music Scholarship Committee, 1953-1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Board of Education, 1936-1962 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Benefit Contracts, 1937-1942 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Benefits: Parsifal; Carmen, 1938-1941, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Benefit: Parsifal, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Benefits, Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 25th Anniversary Clippings (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Publicity, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Publicity, 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Publicity, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Publicity, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - String Faculty (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Mrs. Jane Inge (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Anecdotes from a Survey of Attitudes toward Music, Radio, etc., 1941 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Survey may be of the Pitt St. area of the Lower East Side in New York City.
  - Statistics, 1936-1950 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Statistics, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Statistics, 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Statistics, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Statistics, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Statistics, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Statistics, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Statistics, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Statistics, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Statistics, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Statistics, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Statistics, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Statistics, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Statistics, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Statistics, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Statistics, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Statistics, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Music School Instruments Issued to Students (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, List of Instruments Issued to Students (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Alphabetical files of Students (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Music School Ten Year Plan, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Henry Street Settlement Proposal: The Open Door to the Arts on the Lower East Side, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Director's Reports, 1932-1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Director's Reports, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Director's Reports, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Director's Reports, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Director's Reports, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Director's Reports, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Music School Committee Minutes, 1947-1954 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Music School Committee Minutes, Notes, 1949-1952 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Music School Committee Minutes, Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Music School Committee Minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Music School Committee Minutes, Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Music School Committee Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Music School Committee Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Music School Budget, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Music School Budget, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Music School Budget, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Music School Programs, Reports, Etc., 1948-1962 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Music School Programs, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Helen Hall's Music School Correspondence, 1935, 1948-1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Henry Street Arts Center Building (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - National Guild of Community Music Schools (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Samuel Weschler, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Music School Strike Material, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Music School Problems (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Building Problems, Violations and Plans, 1960-1964 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Violations: 8 Pitt St., 466 Grand St. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Financial Ledgers, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 4)
- Series 2: Student Registration Cards, 1932-1969
  Series 2 contains 22 record storage boxes of student registration cards. The student cards are organized into several sets according to date span. Within each set, cards are usually filed alphabetically. There are also 4 boxes containing faculty record cards; index cards listing music books, scores, and texts; business cards for music companies, tuners and other service providers; and cards on supporters of the school. There are about 35,000 of these types of cards, combined, spanning 1932 to1969.
  Faculty cards may include name, teaching position, date(s) of employment, and reason for leaving. Student cards may include name, date, address, occupation, birth date, birth place, parents' name(s), parents' birth place, parents' occupations, nationality, religion, date of previous study, current subject studied, name of teacher, and fee schedule.
  - Registration Cards, S-W, 1934-1937 (Box 6)
  - Registration Cards, 1929-1960 (Box 7)
  - Registration Cards, 1933, 1955-1956 (Box 8)
  - Registration Cards, 1930-1934 (Box 9)
    5" x 8" cards
  - Registration Cards, K-Z, no date (Box 9)
    4" x 6" cards
  - Registration Cards, S-Z, 1940s-1960s (Box 9)
  - Registration Cards, M, 1934-1936 (Box 9)
  - Registration Cards, 1950s (Box 10)
  - Registration Cards, 1950s (Box 11)
    4" x 6" and 5" x 8"
  - Registration Cards, 1969-1970 (Box 11)
    7" cards
  - Registration Cards, 1936-1939 (Box 12)
  - Registration Cards, A-C, 1960s (Box 13)
  - Registration Cards, 1935-1939, 1960s (Box 14)
  - Cards of music books and scores arranged by instrument and composer (Box 15)
  - Supporters (Box 16)
    National Suzuki Network teachers; music history texts, autobiographies organized by subject
  - Cards of music scores arranged by instrument and composer (Box 17)
  - Registration Cards, 1940s-1950s (Box 18)
  - Registration Cards, 1949 (Box 18)
    Veterans' GI Bill
  - Registration Cards, D-M, 1960s (Box 19)
  - Registration Cards, 1940s (Box 20)
  - Faculty Cards and Student Registration Cards; G, M-N, P-S, 1960s (Box 21)
  - Registration Cards; G, M-N, P-S, 1960s (Box 22)
  - Business Cards (Box 22)
    music companies, tuners, etc.
  - Student Card files (Box 23)
  - Student Card Files; A-Bur (Box 24)
  - Student Card Files; Bur-Exum (Box 25)
  - Student Card Files; F-Goo (Box 26)
  - Student Card Files; Goo-Kaplan (Box 27)
  - Student Card Files; Kaplan-Lo (Box 28)
  - Student Card Files; Lo-Parsoff (Box 29)
  - Student Card files; Parsons-Ritter (Box 30)
- Series 3. Scrapbooks, 1933-1954
  Series 3 is housed in 2 record center boxes, 3 oversize storage boxes and one legal length document box. Materials in Series 3 include newspaper clippings, photographs, concert programs, and information on benefits on behalf of the school.
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, Photographs (Box 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Miscellaneous, 1933-1939 (Box OS 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Miscellaneous, 1944-1954 (Box OS 2)
  - Programs, 1945-1954 (Box OS 3)
  - Benefits Clippings and Correspondence, 1940 (Box OS 3)
    Carmen
  - Benefits - Clippings and correspondence, 1939, 1941, 1942 (Box OS 4)
    Parsifal
  - Programs, Mozart Orchestra, 1947-1951 (Box OS 4)